<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Solomons blessed land a sermon upon Ecclesiastes X.17. Preached before an extraordinary assembly at Newark upon Trent, May 29. 1660. Being the birth-day of our soveraign lord Charles II. King of Engladnd, [sic] &amp;c. / By Samuel Brunsell rector of Bingham in Notting.</title>
            <author>Brunsell, Samuel, 1619 or 20-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1033_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867880</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168912</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168912)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1033[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Solomons blessed land a sermon upon Ecclesiastes X.17. Preached before an extraordinary assembly at Newark upon Trent, May 29. 1660. Being the birth-day of our soveraign lord Charles II. King of Engladnd, [sic] &amp;c. / By Samuel Brunsell rector of Bingham in Notting.</title>
                  <author>Brunsell, Samuel, 1619 or 20-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.C. for Henry Seile over against St. Dunstans Church in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: Solomons blessed land.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes X, 17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168912:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Solomons BLESSED LAND</p>
            <p>A SERMON UPON ECCLESIASTES X. 17. Preached before an Extraordinary Aſſembly AT <hi>NEW ARK</hi> upon <hi>TRENT, May</hi> 29. 1660.</p>
            <p>Being the Birth-day of our Soveraign Lord CHARLES II. KING of <hi>ENGLAND, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Brunſell</hi> Rector of <hi>Bingham</hi> in <hi>Notting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Seile</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:168912:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168912:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SOLOMONS</hi> BLESSED LAND.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLES. X. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed art thou, O Land, when thy King is the Son of Nobles, and thy Princes eat in due ſeaſon, for ſtrength, and not for drunkenneſs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's very neceſſary in all meetings, eſpecially thoſe of a more publick concernment, that men ſhould firſt underſtand the occaſion, and not be like that rabble of <hi>Epheſus</hi> in their tumultuous concourſe, of whom 'tis ſaid,
<note place="margin">Act. 19.32.</note> 
               <hi>That the greateſt part knew not wherefore they were come together:</hi> or like unto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty in our later remembrances, that had loſt the diſtinction between their dayes of <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> and <hi>Humiliation;</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the commonneſs of an hypocritical Sacrifice, with which not only men, but even God himſelf had been wearyed, or through the miſ-apprehenſion and miſ-applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſubject, whereby in the way of an inverted grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, thanks have been frequently ſent up to Heaven for the deſtructive proſperity of our ſins; and men have been hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the greateſt benefits; in ſuch ſort that <hi>as</hi> they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented and bewailed their neceſſary duties, by putting ſome conſiderable parts of their Chriſtian obligations into the black Catalogue of their mock-confeſſions, <hi>ſo</hi> have they not fail'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168912:3"/>to bleſs even God himſelf for their Errors and Preſumptions. To the end therefore that none who hear me, may be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the intent and deſign of this preſent Aſſembly, I ſhall acquaint you with it much in the words of the Pſalmiſt; 'Tis <hi>to ſerve the Lord with gladneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 100.</note> 
               <hi>and come before his preſence with a ſong: to wait in his gates with thanksgiving and in his Courts with praiſe; to be thankful unto him and ſpeak good of his Name: for that the Lord is gracious, and his mercy is everlaſting, and his truth endureth from generation to generation;</hi> that is, from the <hi>father</hi> to the <hi>ſon.</hi> And bleſſed be he that ſitteth on the Throne, and liveth for ever and ever, that hath performed that mercy and that truth to our <hi>David</hi> and his Seed, that gave, as on this day, to the Crowned Martyr a Royal Confeſſor (ſuch had the ſins of an unthankful people made them) to be the Heir at once both of his Crowns and Vertues.</p>
            <p>If publique bleſſings deſerve publique thanks and ſolemn commemorations; and that Nation be ſo bleſſed whoſe King is the Son of Nobles; and that bleſſing take its original from the birth of that Son, our thanks doubtleſs ſhould keep time with the bleſſing. For if men be greedy to have bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings beſtowed upon them, upon the earlieſt ſenſe and firſt ſuggeſtion of their wants, 'tis fit they ſhould be careful to date their Thankſgivings from the very firſt riſe and birth of their bleſſings. The birth of a King, that is <hi>the Son of Nebles,</hi> is <hi>a bleſſing</hi> in the judgment of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt both of Kings and men. And that bleſſing too is of no mean value, nor of a ſmall extent, 'tis a Publique, a National bleſſing, that by which <hi>a whole land</hi> is bleſſed: <hi>Bleſſed art thou, O Land,</hi> &amp;c. And this is the bleſſing of this Land, through the tender mercy of our God, whereby the day-ſpring from on high hath viſited us, even at this day. Our King is the Son of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and our Princes eat in due ſeaſon, for ſtrength and not for drunkenneſs. Nobility of deſcent (as that imports gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity not only of bloud, but of ſpirit alſo) and temperance in life, are very eminent and conſiderable parts of thoſe Princely excellencies that qualifie the Perſon by whom our Land is bleſſed, and that render him the Darling both of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth. And this, I doubt not, will be acknowledged
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168912:3"/>by all but the ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> the <hi>Shimei's</hi> of the time,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.26.</note> or the company of <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then our duty and buſineſs is thankfulneſs, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth a bleſſing. Now as men value the bleſſing, ſo they diſpoſe themſelves for thankſgiving. Be the bleſſing what it will, if men do not eſteem it ſo, they can never be thankful. Bread made of the corn of Heaven, even the very food of Angels, will be loath'd as light, by thoſe that do not reliſh it. <hi>Not this man, but Barabbas,</hi> crie the Jews; though that man were their King, the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> their Saviour. So ſome ſtill ſay even unto God himſelf, <hi>Depart from us, we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes.</hi> If then men cannot be thankful for that which they do not value; it muſt needs be pertinent to our preſent purpoſe well to underſtand the nature of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which at this time calls for our thanks. The thanks muſt be publique, for the bleſſing is no leſs: all that do not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully forſake their own mercies, have a ſhare and intereſt in it. And the words before us, are very proper to give us an accompt of its value, which from them I ſhall endeavour to do by theſe degrees, ſhewing,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That 'tis a bleſſing for a Land to be under a Government.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That 'tis yet a further degree of bleſſing to be under a King.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That Kingly Government is then most bleſſed, when the King is the Son of Nobles, and the Princes eat in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for ſtrength and not for drunkenneſs.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>How far we of this Nation are more immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in theſe great improvements of bleſſing, will appear in the Applications.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, if government were not a bleſſing, the world might have done well without it, each man being left to the dictate of his own will, and acting according to the ſenſe of his own judgment, and the impulſe of his own luſts. And ſo things might poſſibly have ſtood, if every one had been ſufficient for himſelf, without being forc't to call for the aids of others, if the ground had not been curſt for mans ſake, but Nature had of her own accord, and from her own ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, unaskt, brought forth all requiſite ſupplies, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd them <hi>gratis</hi> to the needs and acceptance of all. But
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168912:4"/>ſin had otherwiſe devis'd, and Juſtice hath accordingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd.
<note place="margin">Job 5.7</note> Man now is <hi>born to labour as the ſparks fly upward,</hi> and the decree is not to be reverſt; <hi>In the ſweat of thy brows, thou ſhalt eat bread all the dayes of thy life.</hi> Mans ſtrengths are now weak, his wants many, his dangers ſudden, his fore-ſight ſhort, his reaſon perplext, and his heart deceitful. A little care diſtracts him, a little pain tires him, the leaſt accident afflicts him. However, care he will, and labour he muſt, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his own preſervation; the deſire whereof being root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our very beings, the means to effect it could not but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the natural imployment of mankind, and ſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of food and rayment, with places of repoſe and ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are the firſt of all humane cares. But man finding himſelf capable of further enjoyments, and his appetite being looſe and unconfin'd, he is ſtill craving and asking, <hi>who will ſhew him any good?</hi> reſts not ſatisfied with neceſſaries, but affects <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity</hi> and abundance. Not only nature muſt be ſatisfied, but the ſenſe muſt alſo be pleas'd, and the body pamper'd, by introducing <hi>luxurie</hi> and <hi>vanity</hi> the creature of fancy and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, acted by the inſatiable luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the eyes, and the pride of life. Hence, as men are able, they ſtore themſelves with proviſions for all theſe deſires; ſome of which, thoſe chiefly of the firſt ſort, are indeed lawful and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable in due meaſure and order. But men were not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, neither would they ſtop there: their deſires being much enlarg'd, they ſuit their endeavours thereafter, which that they may employ ſucceſsfully without interruption, and alſo ſecure to themſelves the poſſeſſion of what their induſtry ſhould procure, they could not but diſcern the neceſſity of conſtituting ſuch <hi>a power,</hi> as might be ſufficient for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>protection</hi> and <hi>ſafety.</hi> Since therefore all power is either of one or of many, and thoſe many muſt needs be either divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or united; if ſingle power be weak and unequal, and if power divided cannot ſtand, then that power which alone is ſufficient for the fore-mentioned purpoſes, muſt needs be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which it cannot be but in <hi>government,</hi> through an union of powers in a Soveraign, which union neceſſarily preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a transferring or ſurrender of the ſingle divided powers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168912:4"/>to him or them that are to uſe them conjoyn'd for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of each particular. The ſtate of men under ſuch power is <hi>Government,</hi> which we have affirmed to be a <hi>bleſſing</hi> from the authority of the Text, and ought to be ſo eſteemed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</p>
            <p n="1">1. By it a Land is delivered from an infinite number of the ſaddeſt and moſt inſupportable evils, which, without ſuch Government, cannot poſſibly be prevented or remedyed. Now thoſe evils being no leſſe then War and all its wilde retinue; whatever miſchiefs, outrages, confuſions, deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and deſolations, either are or can be committed by the inſolence and violence of armed rage and fury, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction or reſtraint, upon the Lives and Liberties, Eſtates, or Perſons of men, muſt needs be imputed to the want of that power which ſaves and protects thoſe that ſubmit to it, from all ſuch Miſeries and Calamities, as know no bound nor end, but the mercileſſe utmoſt cruelty of an irreparable and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall ruine. For where there is no Government, every man becomes his own Judge, and admits no meaſures or rules of right or wrong, but his own irregular and inſatiable appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite; which cannot fail of being encountred with the like in others, who will be as impatient of not having their wills in oppoſition to his, as he of not having his in oppoſition to theirs. A man being left to his own ſingle defence and aid, to act by his own inſtinct, to protect himſelf by his own ſole power, and to uſe that power to what purpoſes he pleaſeth, is not withheld from doing any miſchief to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that himſelf ſhall judge conducing to his own benefit or content, as tending either to his neceſſary ſafety and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, convenience, pleaſure, luxury or wantonneſſe. Now from whence come the greateſt Plagues and Judgments? <hi>Come they not from diſſenſions, diviſions and oppoſitions, from Wars and Fightings?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4.1. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>And from whence come Wars and Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings among you? come they not hence, even of your luſts that war in your members? Ye luſt and have not, ye kill and deſire to have, and cannot obtain, ye fight and war, yet ye have not:</hi> Which would not be, were mens Luſts curb'd by Laws, and the exerciſe of a Soveraign power in a fix'd or well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168912:5"/>order'd Government, which is alſo therefore a bleſſing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</p>
            <p>Secondly, No outward bleſſing, whether conducing to mans being and neceſſary preſervation, or to his well-being, can for any while with any the leaſt ſatisfaction or ſecurity be poſſeſs'd or enjoyed without it. If it be a bleſſing for men to have protection for their perſons, leiſure and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to provide things honeſt either for preſent or future uſe, freedome and ſafety in the enjoyment, vindication from wrongs and injuries, which ſometimes may and will happen: To have the avarice of ſome, the pride and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of others curb'd and reſtrain'd, that they may not be made a prey to the inſolent rage and rapine of every deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and inſulting Villain, and by all manner of licentious, lawleſs and barbarous Uſages, to be devoured and torn in pieces; then needs muſt Government be reckoned in the firſt rank of temporall bleſſings, as comprehending all, ſince by it a remedy is provided for thoſe evils, that otherwiſe muſt needs overtake us, and ſwallow us up; and ſupplies are procur'd for thoſe wants, which, if not provided for, muſt needs render our ſubſiſtence impoſſible.</p>
            <p>By this we many ſee, that if there were ſuch a thing in Nature as a ſtate of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Liberty,</hi> which ſome have fancyed; yet the conſequences of that Liberty being endleſs ſtrife and contention; as much as men value Liberty, 'twere better for them to endure the greateſt grievances of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt Diſcipline, then the ſad Calamities of a miſtaken Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Freedome <hi>from</hi> Government makes it free for every one to do what miſchief he pleaſes; it withdrawes men from the regular power of ſome <hi>one</hi> or ſome <hi>few,</hi> and ſubjects them to the lawleſs arbitrary power and inſolence of <hi>all.</hi> But freedome <hi>in</hi> Government ſubjects you to the juſt and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly power of ſome, and frees you from the mercileſs cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of every malicious Cut-throat, and the inexorable fury of any rude multitude.</p>
            <p>Beſides, though <hi>freedome in Naturalls</hi> be a perfection, as when the body is in ſuch a ſtate of health and ſtrength, as that it can freely exerciſe any proper motion, endure any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168912:5"/>labour or hard-ſhip; or the mind apply it ſelf readily and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly to the conſideration of any proportionable object, yet it is not ſo <hi>in morals;</hi> there the caſe is far otherwiſe. Now men help and benefit, or elſe hurt and hinder one another, <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their morals,</hi> as their wills act and are effective, <hi>then by their naturals.</hi> And therefore nothing can be more conducing to happineſs, then to have that liberty, by which men have a freedom to evil, limited and reſtrain'd. For, if the acts of ſin be damnable, the power, as ſuch, muſt needs be very danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and, ſo far forth, not at all deſirable. 'Tis the honour and perfection of God, as to his Truth, that <hi>he cannot lie;</hi> and,
<note place="margin">Numb. 3.19. Gen. 18.25.</note> as to his Juſtice, that being <hi>Judge of all the world</hi> he cannot but do right; nor can he deny himſelf. And 'tis the happineſs of triumphant Saints to be rais'd above both the liberty of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the power of ſuffering.
<note place="margin">Luke 16.26.</note> 
               <hi>Between us and you there is a great gulf fixed, ſo that they which would paſs from hence to you cannot; neither can they paſs to us that would come from thence.</hi> And even in this ſtate of moral freedom or rather imperfection, in which we now are, the more any man by the ſtrength of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Religion, diligent endeavour, and long cuſtom and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, hath made the doing of any vitious act very difficult for him and next to impoſſible, the better man he is, no doubt, and the nearer to perfection. Were a man to go over a narrow Bridge from whence he might eaſily fall; to have both ſides ſo rail'd in, that he had not a liberty to tumble down head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, were, doubtleſs, no diſadvantage, not had he any reaſon at all to complain of that reſtraint: A drowning man alſo naturally quits his liberty of letting go any thing he gets hold on, that hath but the leaſt appearance of conducing ought to his ſafety. Sin is one of the greateſt enemies we have, and 'tis a liberty indeed to be able to commit a ſin or not; but that power being the power of an enemy; he, that, if he might be quite freed from it, would yet be able to ſin, by the exerciſe of that deſtructive power, cannot be imagined in the leaſt to conſult his own ſafety or welfare; but muſt rather be lookt on as one <hi>that hath made a covenant with death, and is with hell at agreement,</hi> as we read of ſome, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.15. And if every ſingle perſon deſpiſing the bleſſing of government,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168912:6"/>would have a liberty <hi>to do what himſelf liſteth, and is right in his own eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 17.6. Gen. 16.12.</note> as we read it was in <hi>Iſrael, when there was no King there;</hi> 'tis true, <hi>his hand</hi> like <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> might be <hi>againſt every man;</hi> but then 'tis as true that <hi>every mans hand muſt needs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be againſt him.</hi> Now which is more eligible and deſirable, to have it in my ſingle choyce, to act what I pleaſe upon others, whileſt every perſon beſides my ſelf (not one of which perhaps but may equal me on ſome occaſion or other) ſhall have the like freedom to act what he liſts upon me, or that we be both reſtrain'd? What good ſhall that weak and indefen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible liberty do to me that am but one againſt a multitude, by every one of which I may at pleaſure be oppreſt and ruin'd? And how then is it poſſible I ſhould reaſonably promiſe to my ſelf the leaſt comfortable enjoyment of any thing though but for a minute? and what's my life, if I have no enjoyment? What enjoyment can I have where there's no ſecurity? And what ſecurity can there be without peace? And what peace can be expected where there is no bond of government to bind and hold men to it?</p>
            <p>What hath thus been ſaid of government <hi>in the general</hi> is applicable both to the Church and ſtate <hi>in particular,</hi> whether we conſider the ſame perſons either as men or Chriſtians, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is abſolutely neceſſary to the ſafety and welfare, as of their humanity, ſo alſo of their Chriſtianity. For ſhould there be allowed in <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> a liberty for men to profeſs &amp; practiſe what they pleaſe, 'twere nothing but <hi>an empty name,</hi> ſince it can have no ſenſe any further, then as it ſignifies ſuch a Profeſſion as laies upon all thoſe that undertake it, ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints of ſubjection &amp; obligation to others. For, if there be no ſuch bond or obligation, there can be no union; &amp; where there is no union, there can be no Society Corporation or body of men; where no body, no members; where no members, no Church. But Chriſt is the Saviour of his body, which is the Church; and in the body there are many members, yet but one body.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>For</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>as the body is one and hath many members, and all the members of that one body being many are one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo alſo is Chriſt. For by one ſpirit we are all baptized into one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, bond or free: and have been all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168912:6"/>made to drink into one ſpirit, for the body is not one member,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. If they were all one member, where were the body? But now are they many members, yet but one body.</hi> To be a Chriſtian then is to be one of many, of many in ſociety or in a body. The ſelf-dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Enthuſiaſt is but one by himſelf, above Church-Society, and ſo above Church-work, and ſo cannot be of the body, and ſo no Chriſtian. The Independent is but one in a private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and is next to that which is next to none; but the Church is a body comprehenſive of whole Nations, Jews and Gentiles. And all the multitude of Chriſtians that in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Nation, do hold the Catholique Apoſtolique Faith, and profeſs obedience to the ſame, do therefore make one National Church, becauſe they all ſubmit to one and the ſame Eccleſiaſtical government, by the Laws and direction where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of every one that is duly made a member, is bound to act in ſuch ſort as not to violate the common faith or the publique peace. Common people therefore are abuſed by their falſe teachers, when they are made to believe that thoſe who aſſert a National Church, underſtand no more to be required to make a man a member of ſuch a Church, (ſuppoſe, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſake, <hi>this Church of England</hi>) then that he be born up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground, or be deſcended from <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parents. If any thing had been ſufficient to check the impudence of ſuch bold impoſtors, the offices themſelves, as they are publiquely expoſed to every ones view, might have ſecur'd us from ſo groſs a ſlander.</p>
            <p>But how much ſoever theſe <hi>Depopulators of Churches</hi> may ſport themſelves with their own deceivings, &amp; think they have gain'd ſome great advantage by their <hi>ſmall incloſures,</hi> 'twill yet be very hard for them to make good any claim to the eſſential requiſites of a Church. For albeit a multitude of Independent Congregations might all together be called a Church, yet they cannot make ſuch a body as a Church ſhould be, wherein the act of ſome muſt neceſſarily lay an obligation upon all the reſt, which is quite contrary to the Independency and ſelf-ſufficiency of their ſingle Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Such Societies therefore make no greater diſtinction from Univerſal Liberty in each individual, then a liberty or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168912:7"/>independency in each private family would do, which hath none of the fore-mentioned inconveniencies remedied by ſo ſmall and inconſiderable an union. Such a State therefore is no better then a State of factious Diviſion or <hi>religious War,</hi> inconſiſtent with Chriſtianity, which is a <hi>religious peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's evident then, that the want of a fixed Government, whether in <hi>Church or State,</hi> doth utterly deſtroy the being and conſtitution of <hi>either.</hi> What miſchief it createth, what fires it kindles, both in the one and the other, muſt needs be obvious to any conſidering perſon, and you cannot but have ſufficiently learnt it from our own late ſad experience. How have Errors and Hereſies, Blaſphemies and Schiſms, Impiety and Profaneneſs, Atheiſm and Barbariſm, robbing both of men and God, invaded and over-run us? What Seas of bloud, what inundations of wickedneſs like fire and brimſtone from the mouth of Hell, have as the waters of the Ocean without a bound at once broke in and overwhelm'd us? During that calamitous ſtate of things, how have we been ſhifted through all the ſhapes and forms of uſurped Tyranny? What whirling and rotation from one project to another, even as many as the hypocritical madneſs, or phantaſtique levity of every <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy dreamer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 8.</note> that had but the confidence to <hi>deſpiſe Dominion and to ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> could invent? How have the wayes of Zion mourn'd and all her gates been deſolate? How have her Prieſts ſighed, and her Virgins been afflicted? for her beauty was all departed, and her Princes became like Harts that finde no paſture, and are gone before the purſuer. Yea how hath the daily Sacrifice been taken away, the ſolemn feaſts and Sabbaths been forgotten, and the King and the Prieſt been deſpiſed? The precious ſons of Sion, comparable to fine gold, have been eſteemed as earthen pitchers, and the work of the hands of the Potter. They that did feed deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately have been deſolate in the ſtreets, and they that were brought up in Scarlet have embraced dunghils. Thoſe that were purer then ſnow and whiter then milk, more ruddie in body then Rubies, and their poliſhing of Saphir, their viſage hath been blacker then a coal, neither have they been known in the ſtreets, their skin hath cleaved to their bones and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168912:7"/>withered and become like a ſtick. Theſe are the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a ſubverted power, ſufficient to inſtruct us how great a bleſſing it is for a Land to be built and ſetled upon the laſting Foundations of a well-order'd Government.</p>
            <p>From hence alſo we may note the folly or rather madneſs of <hi>ſedition</hi> and <hi>innovation,</hi> when once a good Government is well fixt and eſtabliſht. It is I confeſs a matter of very great eaſe to finde ſome faults in things not capable of abſolute perfection, and ſo to remove one evill as to introduce a worſe: But to mend that, which the wiſdom and experience of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and thoſe the beſt and pureſt Ages have determin'd, is either the cheat of <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> or the confidence of Fools. Whatever men may promiſe to themſelves, or pretend to others, the true and naturall effect of ſuch Reforming, can certainly be nothing but meer Anarchy and Confuſion, not more deſtructive to any then to the firſt Deſigners. An abuſed people may for a while indeed reſign their judgement to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit faith, and God in his juſt judgement may give them over, that received not the truth with love, to ſtrong deluſions to believe a lie; but ſo ſoon as the ſtroke of Divine Juſtice hath made them feel their Errour, they are no leſs eager to throw down thoſe popular Idols, then they were zealous before to enſhrine and worſhip them. To draw men into folly and danger, by abuſing their hopes and betraying their Intereſts, is very feſible; but to abuſe their hopes in betraying thoſe their Intereſts, and not to incur their rage, may be concluded impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Various and numberleſs are the ſhifts and perplexities, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite the hazards, and ſad are the events which ſuch Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors do neceſſarily draw both upon themſelves and others. In nothing do they ſuffer more then in thoſe very points for which at firſt they engage. While they crie out for <hi>liberty,</hi> they make both themſelves and their credulots followers <hi>the ſervants of Corruption;</hi> while Sea and Land is compaſſed to make a <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> the man becomes ten times more the childe of the Devil then before. While all that is cryed up holds forth nothing but <hi>truth and peace,</hi> nothing ſuffers more then the one by <hi>lying and perjurie,</hi> and the other by <hi>tumult and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection:</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168912:8"/>And then no marvail too, if <hi>Juſtice,</hi> that was ſo loudly called for, be turned into Wormwood, the very Gall and bitterneſs of Cruelty and Oppreſſion: And the whole <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf, the ſecuring or refining whereof is evermore the great wheel in all popular Commotions, be ſo far adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, as to degenerate at laſt into manifeſt Apoſtaſie and perfect Atheiſme. The beſt recompenſe that ſuch Deceivers can expect, for theſe their pernicious Counſels and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous practiſes, is a ſhame not to be wiped away; and the infamy of thoſe vile arts of hypocriſie and falſhood, ſlander and detraction which they were fain to exerciſe, thereby to draw the ignorant and unwary multitude into a diſlike and hatred of the power to which they owe their ſubjection and their peace.</p>
            <p>But 'tis to be hoped that <hi>experience</hi> hath <hi>now</hi> taught the moſt, what <hi>reaſon</hi> might have done <hi>long ſince,</hi> that it's the great concernment of any people to be fully perſwaded that the benefits they receive from a good Government, are far more valuable then any thing that their Governours are able to receive from them, who feel indeed their own eaſe and enjoyments, but are leſs ſenſible of the others cares and burdens.</p>
            <p>Men alſo that did own no other <hi>rule</hi> to order and juſtifie their ſeditious attempts then <hi>providence,</hi> nor any other <hi>Judge</hi> of Controverſie then <hi>ſucceſſe,</hi> have now a very fair occaſion given them, either to quit their Principles, or deny their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, but ſhall doubtleſs do beſt to do both.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe who in order to the unſetling of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are ſo apt to cavil at the directions of them that have the overſight of the Church, and to traduce ſome prudent accommodations of things to emergent occaſions as irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Impoſitions, they ſhall do well to learn the uſe of ſo much modeſty, as not to paſs opprobrious cenſures upon the acts of their Governours, becauſe themſelves were not made acquainted with the grounds of what they did; and not fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine that there can be no reaſon, which themſelves do not underſtand. Every one is not ſo happy as to be able of himſelf to diſcern the true and proper cauſes of things.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168912:8"/>However, if they will not be ſo <hi>charitable</hi> (which they ought to be, even to the good name of any obſcure perſon) as to think and ſpeak the beſt, yet they might be at leaſt ſo <hi>juſt,</hi> as firſt to inquire of thoſe that could inform them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they uſurp the ſeat of Judgement and pronounce their ſentence. Certainly, <hi>contempt of Authority,</hi> the immediate parent of Diſobedience, Schiſme and Rebellion, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per iſſue of ſlandering the footſteps of Superiours, is of far worſe conſequence then the ignorance or diſſatisfaction of any private judgement. The Apoſtles Caution, if hearkened to and obſerved, would doubtleſs prevent the petulant raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch intemperance. <hi>I ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>through the grace given unto me, to every one that is among you; that no man think more highly of himſelf then he ought to think, but that he think ſoberly according to diſcretion;</hi> or as others read it, <hi>that no man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to underſtand above that which is meet to underſtand, but that he underſtand according to ſobriety, as God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of Faith.</hi> The Originall is too elegant to be exactly rendered in any other Language.</p>
            <p>For men alſo to claim and contend for an arbitrary power or liberty in the publique Offices of the Church (which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly (if any) had need to be guided and regulated by the publique wiſdom of the whole Government) and by vertue of that liberty to preſcribe or dictate at pleaſure what to them ſhall ſeem good; as it gives occaſion to defile the Worſhip with polluted offerings, ſo it moſt affectedly diſparages the piety and judgment of a Church and State, as fit to be rejected in compariſon of the Scepticall and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultory Fancy of an Opinionative Novelliſt. And then, ſince to have the Government of any people, is nothing elſe but to have a power to diſpoſe of their actions according to ones will, thoſe actions chiefly that are of a publique nature; he that upon his own private account aſſumes the authority of dictating to a Congregation, or making them all act the ſame with himſelf, and not according to the legall appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, doubtleſs, arrogates, in a matter of great importance, the exerciſe of a piece of arbitrary Government, to very ill purpoſes. Such practiſe, whatever colours may be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168912:9"/>us'd to varniſh it, is not really effectuall to mens greater edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, or a better oeconomy, but rather ſubſervient to the vain oſtentation of a perſonall ability, and diſplaying the cheap Inventory of ſome ſtriped Furniture to the itching ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of ignorant and deluded people; who, if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by this means more receptive of Errour, and more apt to be cloven into factious ſeparations, muſt needs be expos'd to a very great temptation of attempting things inconſiſtent with Rule and Order, and conſequently deſtructive both to the publique and themſelves.</p>
            <p>I rather urge this, becauſe <hi>our Government</hi> having Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians for its Subjects, our late Contentions having been kindled at this fire from the Sanctuary: the effect whereof, among other ill Conſequences of Subverted Government, hath been the offering of ſtrange fire upon Gods Altars, by Prieſts made of the loweſt of the people. The more have they to anſwer for, that ſtill bring fuel to keep them alive, rather then water to quench and extinguiſh them. To ſpeak that which I take to be clear and evident reaſon: when men meet together in publique to ſerve God by Prayers, Praiſes, Thankſgivings, Sacramentall Devotions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the queſtion is, Whether they ſhall act every one apart by the ſuggeſtion of his own ſpirit and fancy without any Rule and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or not? If ſo, then another coming in muſt needs ſay they are mad: Where's the Union, where the Communion of Saints? If they muſt not act in Diviſion and Confuſion, but in Conjunction and Order; of neceſſity they muſt all agree in one form, and proceed as that ſhall direct. The queſtion now is, <hi>Who ſhall preſcribe that Form?</hi> Let the Anſwer be, Such as may moſt reaſonably pretend to be moſt able, prudent and judicious, to dictate that which is fit to be offered unto God by us all; who can beſt aſſure us that we do not preſent a blinde or a lame Sacrifice. Now would it not be a ridiculous preſumption for any private ordinary Miniſter to ſtep in, and ſay: I have a gift, and can hold it forth <hi>extempore,</hi> and you ſhall do better to give me occaſion to exerciſe, and let you ſee that I have that gift, then to take that <hi>Form</hi> which the Church with the approbation of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168912:9"/>State in ſo many Convocations, Synods and Parliaments, in ſolemn manner upon the wiſeſt deliberation, upon a nice and careful diſquiſition of all particulars, were able to contrive and fit to all the ordinary and extraordinary neceſſities of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? Might it not juſtly and reaſonably be replyed, We are much better provided for and ſecur'd by the deliberate Judgment, and Wiſdom, and Piety of the Church and State in this matter, then by the ſuddain incoherent effuſions of your inconſiderate fancy that are but One, and that ſo ſmall a Member, and ſo much inferiour every way perhaps to the leaſt of them? When we pray with you, <hi>our</hi> ſpirit of prayer is reſtrained by a form of <hi>your</hi> deviſing, which what it will prove in the tryall, <hi>you</hi> as yet know not <hi>your ſelf,</hi> much leſs can <hi>we.</hi> As it is not <hi>your</hi> buſineſs in this caſe to proclaim your gifts, ſo neither is it <hi>ours</hi> to admire you for them. Whatever reaſon you may have to think your ſelf abler and fitter to dictate to us, then the ableſt of the Church, in ſo many full and ſolemn Aſſemblies in ſeverall Ages, after ſuch clear and ſtrict debates of all queſtions and doubts that did then offer themſelves to their piercing obſervations, <hi>we,</hi> ſure, can have no imaginable reaſon to think ſo of <hi>you.</hi> If <hi>you</hi> may be in the right, much more may <hi>they:</hi> If <hi>they</hi> may be miſtaken in any thing, much more may <hi>you:</hi> It can therefore be no leſs then madneſs in us to reject <hi>them</hi> in compariſon of <hi>you.</hi> We know alſo, and are aſſur'd, that, by the Laws of God, we owe obedience to their Authority, from which it is not in your power, ſhould you pretend to more then ever any Pope did, to abſolve us. Beſides, the truth is, our own unhappy experience in this matter is ſuch, that the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned among us have been able to diſcern ſuch miſtakes and abſurdities, yea ſometimes blaſphemies to have fallen from pretenders in this kinde, that our folly would be as inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable as theirs is manifeſt, ſhould we rather chooſe to lean upon ſuch broken Reeds, then on the Church of the living God, the Pillar and the ground of truth. For by its holy care and wiſe direction, the whole publique Worſhip is now ſo compleat in all the parts, and ſo fitted to the occaſions and neceſſities of Chriſtians; moreover for the comely faſhion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168912:10"/>or manner of doing it, all is perform'd with ſuch grave and decent Ceremony, fitted only to keep the mindes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple intent by apt Declarations of their due concurrence, and ſuitable improvements of their zeal and fervour, as alſo to gain a neceſſary regard and reverence to the action, that as the Church knew not how to provide for us better, ſo we have no reaſon to expect any other ſo good, but ſhall rather thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully joyn with the reſt of Gods people happily ſubjected to the ſame Diſcipline, then follow a multitude to do evill. And this we believe muſt needs be more honourable to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by the harmony and beauty, and more effectuall with God by the ſtrength of ſo great an Union, and conſequently much more reaſonable and ſafe for us, then the pert inventions of any the moſt illuminated pretenders.</p>
            <p>They muſt be, I conceive, extremely paſſionate, ſelf-willed and prejudiced, that ſhould hold ſuch a Reply unreaſonable. For certainly we have no cauſe to <hi>fear</hi> any danger from that which commonly men deem, and, by miſtake, have learned to call <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> which muſt needs be more chargeable on ſuch as, in oppoſition to the ſentence of the Church, follow the decrees of their own <hi>private wills</hi> in determining what comes neareſt to the minde and will of God; and in projecting the very frame and method after which a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Chriſtians aſſembled together for the ſervice of God, are to preſent their devotions.</p>
            <p>As little need we to <hi>fear</hi> the ſuſpicion of <hi>Popery,</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorming to that way of publique Worſhip which our Church hath preſcrib'd; when as this Conformity ſtands in a direct oppoſition to that Popery which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves, and alſo our Laws do account and have declar'd for ſuch. For are not Papiſts forbidden, by the the Laws of their own Communion, to joyn in the publique Service of our Church, who yet are permitted to hear the Expoſitions and Sermons of the reformed, accompanyed with ſuch of their prayers as are the preſent dictates of their private ſpirits. And are not the Reformed again on the other ſide generally as liberall and free to them, who, ſhould they joyn in their Maſſes, and thoſe other publique Offices, by which Papiſts diſtinguiſh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168912:10"/>and hold their Communion, would certainly be deem'd Proſelytes by thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> and Apoſtates by the men of their own profeſſion. Doubtleſs, that for which men are called <hi>Recuſants,</hi> and cenſured by our Laws as ſuch, hath more of Popery in it, then hath any ones conformity to the Service of our Church; the denyall of which confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity by the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> being that by which they diſclaim our Communion, is the very eſſence of <hi>Popery,</hi> as that is underſtood to ſignifie <hi>Recuſancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe, who (that they may not ſeem <hi>ſine ratione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanire,</hi> or neglect the neceſſary defenſe, as they think, of their errors and reputations) hold themſelves engaged to juſtifie their diſobedience, by traducing the decent and inſtructive Ceremonies of our Church as ſuperſtitious, or at leaſt a too ſtiffe inſiſting upon ſmaller matters; If the Church <hi>had bidden them do ſome great thing, ſhould they not have done it?</hi> how much more when ſhe requires only ſuch forms, geſtures, or habits, as beſt ſerve to beget that reverence, and expreſs that uniformity, without which all ſolemn actions muſt needs fall into contempt and indecency.</p>
            <p>But 'tis to be hoped, that when upon a moſt ſtrict and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial inquiry with a ſincere heart and ſingle eye, as in his ſight before whoſe eyes all things are naked and open, they ſhall have clearly ſatisfied their Conſciences in the grounds that mov'd them firſt to cenſure, and then to depart from that which themſelves had formerly practiſed, and were obliged to by lawfull Oaths and Subſcriptions; and when they ſhall well have weighed the conſequences, which their eyes have ſeen to flow from their very Principles, and the confeſſed miſcarriages of divers of their chiefeſt and moſt renowned Patrons; they may at length think it not only poſſible for them to erre, but more then probable that they have done ſo in the preſent caſe. The truth is, in many things we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all; and infallibility is no more to be found at <hi>Geneva</hi> then at <hi>Rome,</hi> though the one be for the moſt part as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory in denying the act, as the other the power; and though there be ſo little difference between him, that, upon the cleareſt inſtances, could never be brought to ſay he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168912:11"/>
               <hi>had</hi> erred, and him that ſayes he never <hi>can.</hi> So ſoon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as either their paſſion, prejudice or intereſt, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit faith by which they embrace any thing that is with confidence delivered for ſound and orthodox by thoſe, whoſe perſons, for ſome grave appearances of Learning and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they have in admiration, ſhall give them leave to ſee and conſider what <hi>Superſtition</hi> is? and that as a good meaning cannot juſtifie an evil undertaking, ſo neither can the reputed honeſty of a man of gifts, authoriſe an error either in faith or life; they will no longer look upon the powerfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions of ſequeſtred truth as ſo many Engines of Satan to beat them from their ſtedfaſtneſs; nor on thoſe that have taken ſo much pains to ſave them, as on men of corrupt principles or profane hearts. Indeed when men have for a good while together had quiet poſſeſſion of ſome congruous errour, the leaſt diſturbance proves very afflictive, and thoſe that have long enjoyed the pleaſure of thinking well of themſelves and deſpiſing others, (like men prefer'd to honour in a dream) are much diſquieted upon the firſt opening of their eyes and judgements to perceive the Deluſion. So much more agreeable to naturall corruption is familiar error, then unacquainted truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> But may it not ſeem ſtrange and very improbable, that thoſe who have alwayes been ſo very zealous againſt the formalitie and abuſes of the times, ſhould be ſo much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? Have not godly men long ſince complain'd of faults, and taxed the condition of things amiſs both in Church and State, which (the Government ſtanding as it did) could never be redreſs'd? If the complaint be not true, both <hi>they,</hi> our Ring-leaders, and <hi>we</hi> their cloſe and conſtant followers or rather over-runners, have all this while been deceivers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: and is it likely that ſo many of Gods people, whom we alwayes took and do take to be <hi>the only honeſt party,</hi> ſhould complain without cauſe? Muſt we be look'd upon as men that had no juſt ground for what we laboured for, and took pains with prayer, and preaching, and <hi>faſting, even to ſtrife and debate, and ſmiting with the fiſt of wickedneſſe?</hi> The very life of our Good Old Cauſe, the honour and reputation
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168912:11"/>both of it and our ſelves are herein nearly concern'd: and what alſo <hi>will the world</hi> then <hi>think</hi> of us? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I <hi>anſwer,</hi> even <hi>what it does;</hi> unleſs we ſhall repent and do our firſt works. Either <hi>we or thoſe</hi> muſt be miſtaken, who are far more conſiderable both for numbers and qualities then our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Muſt the Church, the State, the beſt, the wiſeſt, the holyeſt and the learnedſt men be <hi>fools</hi> that <hi>we</hi> may appear <hi>wiſe?</hi> muſt <hi>they all</hi> have erred that <hi>we</hi> may ſeem not to have erred? or be all in the <hi>wrong</hi> that we may be in the <hi>right?</hi> Or will our error become none, and that which is wrong prove right by our not ſeeming to ſee it, by our unwillingneſs to own it, and reſolution to perſiſt in it? Yea, to excuſe us, will Conſcience ceaſe to give in her evidence, or will the righteous Judge, in favour to our incorrigibleneſs forbear to pronounce and inflict his ſentence? That we may be ſafe in our reputation, muſt all former Ages ſuffer in theirs? Muſt Antiquity loſe its reverence, Truth its force, Kings their Majeſty, Parliaments, Convocations and Synods their judgement and authority? Muſt Wiſdom be no more with the Aged, nor Prudence with the Counſellors, nor Inſtruction with the Judges? Muſt ſuch a Noble Army of Martyrs as ſeal'd our Reformation with their bloud, caſt down their Crowns at our polluted feet to lift up our Axes and Hammers? Or rather were it not much more creditable and ſafe for us to engage Poſterity to hide our greater ſhame by a preſent juſt and pious care not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and deride, but cover our Parents nakedneſs in caſe of the leaſt diſcovery?</p>
            <p>Certainly our Fore-fathers (as quick-ſighted, for ought appears to the contrary, as our ſelves) had they been able to ſee and remedy what we think we diſcover and can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, to wit, Errour, Superſtition and folly in their careful Collections and wary Improvements, they would not, by a voluntary guilt, have brought a reproach upon the Nation, and an open infamy upon its Publique Acts, thereby wilfully drawing upon themſelves, the Church and State, the juſt cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and ſcorn of all knowing men. The event certainly and ſucceſs of what they did, compar'd with that of what we have ſince eſſayed to do, muſt needs <hi>juſtifie them</hi> and <hi>condemn
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168912:12"/>us;</hi> nor can our peeviſh obſtinacy prevail with men to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it otherwiſe. Our wiſeſt courſe certainly will be, never to be tampering any more with foundations and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, leaſt, thoſe being ſhaken, the whole pile fall down upon our giddy heads, and bury both us and our Inventions quick in the ruines. So dangerous and deſtructive is <hi>Innovation in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> and ſo vain and troubleſome, as well as infectious, is mens unnatural itch and greedineſs after it: a levity to which either the ignorance or wantonneſs of common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, like the deſire of new, though undecent and uneaſie faſhions, hath been to apt to betray them. <hi>My ſon fear thou the Lord and the King,</hi> ſaith Solomon, <hi>and meddle not with them that are given to change, for their calamity ſhall riſe ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</hi> Prov. 24.21, 21.</p>
            <p>In reaſon, all change ſhould be <hi>for the better,</hi> and ſuch was that which was made from War to Peace; that is, from law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs boundleſs liberty, to Empire, Rule and Government. The motive to the change was good, ſettlement and order being as much better then giddineſs and confuſion (in which the greateſt eaſe and ſecurity a man can promiſe himſelf, is no better then that of ſleeping upon the top of a maſt) as is a calm then a ſtorm, health then ſickneſs, or life it ſelf then death. For what is ſuch a life but <hi>a living death?</hi> or, as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it, <hi>a dying daily?</hi> For men to live, like the wild Beaſts of a Wilderneſs, in the barbarous and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage condition of war, muſt needs be the complement and fulneſs of all earthly miſery. The drawn Sword of a deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Angel cutting down a Nation with <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> was prefer'd by <hi>David before the Sword</hi> of an enemy. But of all War and enmity <hi>Civil War</hi> is the worſt: and this is that which thoſe men chooſe, that affect a <hi>change of Government;</hi> inaſmuch as that change, without a power able to match the Soveraign Power, can never be effected. For the oppoſition of thoſe Powers is <hi>War,</hi> the very worſt of evils, which theſe men chooſe for a remedy of ſomething <hi>they call evil;</hi> which, be it what it will, muſt needs be much better then the worſt; and therefore make their choice moſt unreaſonable, an act of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168912:12"/>madneſs, reproachful even to humanity it ſelf. For what can be thought more ſottiſh then for men ſo far to liſten to to the cry of their own paſſions, or the enchantments of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sorcerers, as to abandon themſelves to miſery by being ingaged in parties and factions, contriving and attempting to ſubvert a lawful power, only to make way for another, and that a greater power (ſuch muſt that needs be, by which the former is expulſt) and ſo more able to oppreſs and grind them, not reſting there neither. For ſuch as have no other title then that of <hi>forcible entrie,</hi> nor any ſurer poſſeſſion then that of <hi>forcible detainer,</hi> do but invite a new force, and raiſe a new power to eject them. How many ſuch turns may one ſucceed another, it is not eaſie to determine. The right owner being once ſet aſide, all other pretenders have one and the ſame title, one juſt as much right as the other, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may ſet up and declare when and how they pleaſe. Now of theſe, there muſt needs be as many as thoſe are whoſe crimes, wants or ambition promoted by cunning, colour'd with ſpecious and hypocritical pretences, and backt with ſome external advantages may incline them to ſupplant the Supreme Authority; from the juſtice whereof, as they could not expect impunity for thoſe crimes, ſo neither from the regular Adminiſtrations thereof, had they reaſon to look ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that their needs ſhould be extraordinarily ſupplyed, or their ambition ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>But how long that diſmal Tragedy may laſt, wherein there are ſo many Actors ready to enter the Stage, each re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd in his turn to ſpin out his part to the utmoſt, till both himſelf and the ſad ſpectators be quite worn out and ſpent, he alone knows <hi>that make Diviners mad, and wars to ceaſe in the earth, that knappeth the Spear in ſunder, and burneth the Chariot in the fire;</hi> ſo far pittying the follies of men, more brutiſh in this then the very brutes themſelves (that act not contrary to that reaſon they never had) as in great mercy to raiſe up ſome to ſtill the rage of man, and tame the beaſts of the people, and ſo lead them forth of that vaſt howling Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, as he ſometimes did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by the hands of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron: Moſes</hi> a Supreme Magiſtrate, and, in corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168912:13"/>with him, <hi>Aaron</hi> a chief Prieſt, both ſuch by the wiſe appointment &amp; conſtitution even of God himſelf, whoſe Government being that of a King or Monarch <hi>(for God is King of all the Earth)</hi> muſt needs be therefore the moſt perfect, as we have affirmed Kingly Government to be <hi>in our ſecond Propoſition,</hi> which comes next to be handled.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>As 'tis a bleſſing for a Land to be under a Government, ſo 'tis yet a further degree of bleſſing to be under a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Abſence or Negation of Government is a State of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Liberty and War; and therefore ſo far forth as the indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals of a multitude ſurrenders their diſperſed powers to the rule and diſpoſal of a Soveraign (be that Soveraign a natural perſon, as a Monarch, or an Artificial, as a Senate or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil made one by a concurrence of voyces) ſo far they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Government, and in a reaſonable expectation of Peace, and no further. To counterpoiſe power with power, as weights do one another in a ballance, till they come to an <hi>aequilibrium,</hi> is to make the ſtate of a people alterable with every the leaſt grain of advantage. And certainly it is next to impoſſible for two diſtinct parties inveſted with equal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to uſe thoſe powers ſo equally, though but for a day, as that the one ſhould make no gain, and the other ſuſtain no loſs. The nearer that Powers are matcht, the more jealous they are of encroachments, and the more apt to reſent and conteſt the leaſt tranſgreſſion of bonds. Nor can that jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie in either party be quencht, but by attempting ſome further ſecurity in an exceſs or uſurpation of power, the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility and ſuſpicion whereof at firſt in each other was the very ſpark that kindled it. Supremacy therefore of Power, as it is Eſſential to Government, ſo can it not be reconcil'd with co-ordination without a plain contradiction. To ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine ſuch power in a people conſidered as ſo many looſe individuals, is to conceive an unity in diviſion, there being as many Soveraigns as men. And to think that ſo great a multitude as the vaſt generality of a people, can joyn and concur in ſuch ſort as to act every one for himſelf, or be otherwiſe embodyed and united, then by being made one term of a relation through the neceſſary poſition of ſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168912:13"/>oppoſite term, is to dream or that which is impoſſible, to wit, of an inferiour without a Superiour; or of a Superiour where none are inferiour. When once a relation is put, the terms are immediately diſtinguiſht, and therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the properties peculiar to each term, by impoſing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection on thoſe that govern, and attributing Supremacy of Power to thoſe that are governed, is to make the ſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the father, or the father become the child of his own ſon. Be it ſo that men, of their own accord, by their own conſent and power, either through chance or choice, are fallen into a relation, yet being once there, they cannot make void or alienate the neceſſary duty, which God by his Law hath thereto firmly annext. A woman by her own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, uncompell'd by any Law of God, makes her ſelf a wife to a man, whom therefore ſhe may be ſaid to have <hi>made</hi> her husband; but being once in that relation, the wife may not, upon <hi>pretenſe</hi> of having <hi>made</hi> that man her husband, reverſe the husbands power, and uſurp authority over him. Much leſs, upon the like pretenſe, may the Subject recall or invert the power of the Magiſtrate; the duty of obedience and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion being by God annex'd to Subjection. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men ſo related <hi>muſt needs be ſubject, not only for wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>but alſo for Conſcience ſake;</hi> whatever the motive or occaſion were that firſt brought them into the relation. This bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit however muſt needs be neceſſarily intended in the erection of any Government, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Subjects may be ſecured, ſo far as is poſſible, from danger and miſchief, through ſtrife, violence and war, in the confuſed tyranny of one another. And that form of Government which <hi>beſt</hi> obtains that, which all Government, as ſuch, doth chiefly if not ſolely intend, muſt needs <hi>be prefer'd</hi> before other forms, notwithſtanding its being obnoxious, as all forms are, through one accident or other, to ſome defects and obliquities. Engines that have many wheels will ſometimes be out of order, though no diſparagement to him that either made or keeps them. And therefore it cannot be expected, that Monarchy with its greateſt advantages ſhould be able to ſatisfie all, or fully put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men. The cleareſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168912:14"/>light in heaven is obſerv'd to have ſome ſpots; and if God himſelf did never pleaſe all, is it poſſible that all ſhould be pleas'd? However, to diſcover a weakneſs or imperfection in any thing is no argument that another is better, no more then it would be for any pretender to prudence and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to conclude himſelf wiſer then <hi>Solomon,</hi> becauſe he is able to charge <hi>Him</hi> with ſome act of folly. Upon ſuch an account, it muſt needs be eaſie for any one to make good his claim to an univerſall precedency. The queſtion is, What <hi>form of Government</hi> is <hi>best?</hi> Not whether that Government only ought to be prefer'd or admitted which is <hi>every way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect?</hi> No ſtate or condition upon earth is ſo: and he that will not be ſatisfied upon any other terms, ſhall roll a ſtone with <hi>Siſyphus</hi> and never be at reſt. Seeing then there always were, are, and will be <hi>defects</hi> in all; certainly that muſt heeds be <hi>beſt,</hi> which hath the <hi>leaſt and feweſt.</hi> And that we ſay is <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> or Monarchy, wherein the Elementall powers of a ſimple and unbodyed people, are drawn together and compacted in a ſingle perſon. The reaſon is this.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the more cloſely Soveraign power is united (as when the Sun-beams are drawn towards a point by a Burning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs) the greater ſtrength and aptitude it hath to obtain its end in the <hi>ſafety</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> of the whole Community. For <hi>theſe</hi> can never be well provided for, if a Magiſtrate want ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſtrength to ſuppreſs all attempts that may be made againſt the Government; or cannot exerciſe that ſtrength ſo ſeaſonably and readily, as by timely Diſcoveries and quick preventions to anticipate or countermine the practiſes of ſuch as are enemies to the publique Peace, which is never more in danger, then when the Authors of ſedition, to which all Governments are ſubject more or leſs, do receive incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from ſuch probabilities of effecting their purpoſes, as the frequency of opportunities and greatneſs of temptations cannot but create and ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Ambition</hi> long for Empire, and be even choak'd with thirſt after power: if <hi>pride</hi> affectedly think it ſelf too good or great to be ſubject: if <hi>paſſion</hi> be impotent and cannot hold it ſelf: if <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>errour</hi> would conteſt by force, what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168912:14"/>they cannot make good by reaſon: if <hi>ignorance</hi> will not ſee the good of Peace and ill of War: if <hi>wantonneſſe</hi> being cloy'd and fall, deſpiſe the Honey-combe, or curſe its own Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and be undone for want of variety or ſomething of a new mode: if <hi>covetouſueſſe</hi> would take and enjoy <hi>all,</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute <hi>nothing</hi> towards the expenſive adminiſtrations of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Juſtice and Order: if <hi>ſelf-love</hi> will be partiall, and blame the Government for thoſe ſufferings which the heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Subject hath incurr'd by his own default: if <hi>ſlothfulneſſe, imprudence, luxury</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> will improve nothing, but ſpend all and be in want, and ſeek unlawfull ſupplies, or contract debts and ſuits: and if all theſe do wilfully and greedily expoſe themſelves to danger by the guilt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of their crimes; how is it poſſible but that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral deſire in man to ſave and preſerve himſelf, ſhould diſpoſe and incline them all to ſecure themſelves by force from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accomptable to that Authority which they know muſt curb and correct their Inſolencies? But then that Soveraign power, which is made perfect in one, to wit in a King or Monarch, muſt needs be beſt plac'd and diſpos'd, becauſe its Government, when well adminiſtred, doth evidently afford both leſſe temptations, and fewer opportunities to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, and alſo leſs hopes of ſecurity and ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>For is it not much eaſier for an aſpiring ſpirit to fancie its being one of a Senate, then one where there is but one, which makes the attempt more deſperate? If Supremacy reſide in a multitude, the natural deſire of <hi>power</hi> will ſcarce penult any active perſon in that number to reſt ſatisfied with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when he may fairly hope to have <hi>all?</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Nec quenquam jam ferre poteſt, Caeſar, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lucan.</note>
               </q> Equality is as offenſive to one as Superiority is to another; and what men deſire and hope for, or are in a poſſibility, to attain, they will attempt, if the fear of a common danger do not interpoſe, or that the partners do not over-highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue each others ſtrength and intereſt.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:168912:15"/>
            <p> Is it not alſo more reaſonable to infer the ſenſe of preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and grievances, which occaſion great calamities, from a <hi>multitude in power</hi> then from One, whoſe experience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſhewes him, that his own private intereſt can be no other then the publique; whereas in the other, the double intereſt of <hi>private</hi> and <hi>publique</hi> diſtinct and frequently op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, like two Maſters requiring contrary ſervices, gives oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to men, whoſe <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>greateſt</hi> kindneſſes do gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally regard themſelves, to pretend the ſervice of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique in order to the ſerving of themſelves, and to ſacrifice the common good to their own private advantage? Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, if <hi>One</hi> may abuſe power, then certainly much more may a <hi>Number;</hi> and if <hi>Ones</hi> ſpending upon a Stock will waſte ſomething of it, what can in reaſon be expected when there are ſo <hi>many</hi> ſpenders?</p>
            <p>And whereas the perſonall diſtance between the Senators and people is not very great, but between the Senators them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves little or none at all; as the greateſt do not exceed the <hi>proportion,</hi> ſo neither are they ſufficiently arm'd againſt the <hi>ſting</hi> of Envy, whoſe venom is ſo killing and infectious. Yet he, that, being no more then one that goes a ſhare in the Soveraignty, and may be abundantly qualified to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the inferiour people, is not plac'd ſo high, as to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their affronts and injuries; muſt needs be inclin'd and inabled to abuſe the publique force in the vindication of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate wrongs, beyond the the limits of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Moreover, when a private eſtate becomes too ſmall and weak to ſupport the honour and dignity of one that is a publique perſon; it cannot prudently be imagin'd, but that the intereſt of corrupted power ſhould be miſapply'd in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing it. And where there muſt needs be place for ſo great a variety of inconſiſtent ends and intereſts among ſo many jealous and ſuſpicious equals, the houſe is ſoon divided, and therefore cannot ſtand, but multitudes are deſtroy'd by the fall. On the contrary, where the diſperſed power of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is moſt cloſely united, as it cannot be more then when it's all reduc'd to one, it muſt needs there be ſtrongeſt, and moſt able to guard the <hi>Palladium</hi> of a Nation, the ſafety of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168912:15"/>that Supreme Power by which alone it enjoyes peace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no injoyment at all.</p>
            <p>Again, where power proceeds upon the concluding advice and executive order or will of <hi>One,</hi> it muſt needs be moſt <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eret</hi> and <hi>expedite.</hi> Where the conſent of many is to be had, that are led by parties and Factions; nothing more practiſed nor practicable then <hi>diſcovery</hi> and <hi>delay,</hi> which are oft-times very fatall and dangerous, chiefly in the riſe and progreſs of ſedition. That a multitude therefore or Aſſembly ſhould ſooner agree and joyn in one, then one perſon with himſelf; that in ſuch a multitude all ſhould be ſincere in their aims and deſigns, and equally deſire and ſeek the common good: That in ſuch a divided adminiſtration there ſhould be leſs corruption and partiality where there is much more tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and opportunity; neither our reaſon nor experience will ſuffer us to believe.</p>
            <p>From hence I ſuppoſe we may ſafely conclude in the generall, that as 'tis a bleſſing for a Land <hi>to be under a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſo 'tis a further degree of bleſſing <hi>to be under a King,</hi> whoſe Government queſtionleſs is the <hi>beſt fence</hi> againſt the dangers of envy, pride and ambition, the <hi>beſt ſtay</hi> and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of every juſt intereſt, the <hi>beſt prevention</hi> and remedy of hoſtility and confuſion, and the <hi>beſt means</hi> of procuring and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſecuring the bleſſed enjoyments of peace.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>the peculiar caſe of this our Nation,</hi> the Subjects whereof were not only <hi>born under,</hi> but alſo <hi>ſworn</hi> to it; Nature, Reaſon and Religion, all concurring to faſten this bleſſing on us, how much better it is for us in all reſpects, as moſt agreeable to our temper and genius, to our Laws and Cuſtomes, moſt approved alſo by long and ſharp tryalls, and that in great variety, hath been of late the ſubject of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pens, that I ſhall not deſcend further into particulars, which I know are evident to the meaneſt obſervation among us. Only we ſhall do well to remember, how happy we have been under it, that thereby, and by the ſenſe of what we have ſuffered for the want of it, we may the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and value the bleſſing of its reſtitution, and being once again <hi>made whole, ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto us.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:168912:16"/>Doubtleſs, nothing could have made us miſerable but the ignorance of our own happineſs. How did Religion and Learning, Laws and Liberties, Truth and Peace flouriſh, and embrace each other? To what a height of glory, and dignity, and wealth, and power were we then arriv'd? Like <hi>Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un,</hi> we were waxen fat, and it had been well for us, if we had not alſo <hi>kicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.15.</note> 
               <hi>and lightly eſteemed the Rock of our ſalvation.</hi> With what reverence, and Freedome, and equity, ſo far as humane infirmities will bear, was Juſtice adminiſtred? when the Subject might ſafely plead his right with the Prince, and was not at all prejudg'd from the liberty of a fair hearing, and a legal ſentence? And for the Church, 'twas not in the power of every ordinary Miniſter, with three or four of his Pariſh to make a Conſiſtory or Spiritual Court, and ſit in judgement over the reſt of his Neighbours, and admit <hi>to</hi> or reject at pleaſure the reſt <hi>from</hi> the Communion of Saints. In which caſe, the cenſur'd perſon, backt with his chief friends and relations, being apt to think himſelf wrong'd, and hardly dealt with by thoſe of his own place, his own Miniſter and fellow-Pariſhioners; what hatred, and variance, and envy, and ſtrife, and malice, and uncharitableneſs muſt needs enſue, and be fomented between Neighbour and Neighbour, Friend and Friend, Miniſter and People? Who, having ſo many common intereſts, and being engaged, by the mutual neceſſities of a daily commerce, in each others concernments, ought certainly to have no ſuch bones caſt among them, by publiſhing the <hi>ſecreta domûs,</hi> as muſt make them not only ſnarl at, but alſo bite and devour one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. All matters of importance ſo neerly concerning men in their ſpiritual intereſts, were wiſely determin'd by the Laws and Conſtitutions of the Church, and the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies thence ariſing, decided by able, choſen and diſintereſſed perſons, that had neither temptation nor incouragement to be partial, which muſt needs provide better for thoſe rights of Chriſtians, then a Neighbour and an Equal, that may have ſo many deflexions to the contrary; beſides want of fitneſs and of ability for ſuch matters, which every ordinary Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter or Pariſhioner in ſo great a body, can with no more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168912:16"/>reaſon be thought furniſht with, then every common Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer or Solicitor be deem'd fit to manage the Office of a Judge.</p>
            <p>As for the due ordering of Gods publique Worſhip in Religious Aſſemblies, private Chriſtians, that have not the leiſure or ability to dive into the depths of Divinity, had better aſſurance given them, that their devout Addreſſes were agreeable to Gods holy Will and Word, then the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain chance of a States-lay-preachers or other ordinary Church-mans fugitive and <hi>extempore</hi> Fancy, which muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce as many diſtinct ſervices in the Church, as there are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations and Inventions of private men. If all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations make one Church, why ſhould they not ſerve God after one and the ſame manner?</p>
            <p>So they ſhould, no doubt, and ſo they did, keeping the <hi>unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And bleſſed be the God of Peace, that hath once more joyn'd us in that Unity, and tyed us again together in that Sacred Bond, which I hope we ſhall never more break aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor caſt away theſe Cords from us! Better and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger we cannot have: good Government an excellent bond of peace, the perfection of outward bleſſings; and of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments the beſt, namely, that of a King, nor ſo only, but Kingly Government in its greateſt perfection, as being then <hi>moſt bleſſeds when the King is the Son of Nobles, and the Princes eat In due ſeaſon, for ſtrength and not for drunkenneſs.</hi> Which is the third and laſt Concluſion, of which briefly and in a word.</p>
            <p>To be a Son of Nobles ſpeaks a relation to the <hi>quality</hi> rather then the <hi>perſon:</hi> in the ſame ſenſe that men of great Atchievements are called the Sons or <hi>honour,</hi> or thoſe that apply themſelves to a more curious ſearch after knowledge, are uſually ſtyled the Sons of <hi>Art;</hi> or, that ſuch are ſaid to be the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.39.</note> who follow the ſaith and works of that friend of God: whoſe ſons and daughters alſo are thoſe that do endear themſelves unto his grace and ſavour, by their conformity to his image; and endeavouring to be perfect, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is perfect.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48.</note> To a contrary
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168912:17"/>purpoſe, the Scripture alſo expreſſeth a vitious perſon, by calling him a <hi>Son of Belial,</hi> or a Childe of the <hi>wicked one,</hi> his Father the Devil. For Children being the lively images of their Parents, by the participation (as of a common nature, ſo) of ſome ſpecial and more peculiar lineaments and apti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, by which they frequently diſcover the Authors of their being; the appellation is very fitly given to thoſe whoſe deſcent is reckon'd according to the pedegree of a <hi>moral,</hi> as well as that of a <hi>natural</hi> generation. And thus a <hi>Son of Nobles</hi> is one, in whom are to be found the ſpecial ſignatures and diſtinctive lineaments of thoſe heroick en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, that, being propagated in a line of ſucceeding ages, do make a race of generous and renowned perſons, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and glory of their times.</p>
            <p>Seeing alſo that the manners of the minde have a great dependence upon the temper of the body, according to that vulgar ſaying, <hi>Mores animi ſequuntur humores corporis;</hi> where the body is rendred exactly ſerviceable to the ſoul, in ſuch ſort as that ſenſuality and paſſion are perfectly kept under the command of Reaſon, (which is the great foundation of the beſt Nobility) no marvail, if the perfections not only of the inferiour, but alſo of the better part (as to ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, propenſities and diſpoſitions) do many times deſcend together, eſpecially where nature is not alloyed and debaſed with ſome vitious, ſordid and unequal mixture, the great unhappineſs of a mercenary and luxurious age. That which in Creatures of a lower rank, we commonly call a good breed, doth not unfitly repreſent the matter. And the care men uſe to procure and preſerve it in <hi>their beaſts,</hi> ſhould, one would think, reproach the neglect of it in <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> A wretchedneſs occaſioned by nothing more then a lazie degenerating from the ſpirit and induſtry of our Noble Anceſtors, or matching the Childe of <hi>Vanity</hi> with the Son of <hi>Honour,</hi> whoſe light thereby grows more dim and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, being firſt waſted by that which impoveriſheth the kinde, and is by <hi>Solomon</hi> diſcredited under the title of <hi>eating in the morning,</hi> as you have it in the Verſe immediately <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> and directly oppos'd <hi>to</hi> my Text, where he makes the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168912:17"/>miſery or ruine of a people, the neceſſary conſequence of childiſhneſs and intemperance in their Rulers: <hi>Wo unto thee O Land, when thy King is a Childe, and thy Princes eat in the morning!</hi> that is, <hi>unſeaſonably:</hi> to which if we add, the vile end and deſign they propoſe to themſelves in ſo doing, not <hi>ſtrength</hi> but <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi> (the perfect contradictory to his end; whom the Text Crowns with temperance) we have a very eminent cauſe diſcovered to us of a Lands weal or woe. For without the due excerciſe of a power Supreme, there can be no good Government, and ſo no bleſſing. But pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is no power in a ſubject indiſpos'd to uſe it, becauſe it can never be well reduc'd to act, there's no ſtrength nor vigor in it, no grace or dignity belonging to it. Whatever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore weakens or empairs the ſtrength either of the minde or body, hath no proportion or congruity with the proper quality and conſtitution of a Governour, the very formality of whoſe Office is to be a man of power. Debauchery therefore; by tranſubſtantiating the man into the beaſt, which was never made for Rule and Dominion, is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly oppoſite to that ſtate and condition by which a Land is bleſſed.</p>
            <p>He then that would truely be ſtyl'd the Son of Nobles, and poſſeſs more then an empty or ridiculous title, muſt not be one that eats <hi>out of ſeaſon,</hi> or that eats for <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi> and ſo takes order, that ſuch meats be procur'd, and in ſuch ſort prepard, as may beſt ſerve to inflame the thirſt, and kindle unnatural fires in the bloud, to the great detriment of that health and ſoundneſs, without which the whole man conſumes and decayes, till at length the enfeebled judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and beſotted reaſon become uſeleſs and inſufficient for the difficult conduct of thoſe great affairs, in the right mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging whereof the bleſſing of a Land doth conſiſt. So Princely and ſtrengthening a vertue is Temperance: The Land, whoſe Rulers and Governours by their authority and examples have planted it to a thriving, is enrich'd and bleſſed by it. So happy alſo are the people whoſe King is the Son of Nobles, above them whoſe Rulers are paſſionate, ignorant, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant; rude and wanton, the uſual properties of children, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168912:18"/>ſuch as is the childe before the Text, who, by being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to <hi>the Son of Nobles,</hi> is ſuppos'd to be of ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble breed, ſome riotous or mean extraction. Which we ſhall not at all think ſtrange, if we conſider how the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their condition muſt needs render their envyed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons odious, and make their power contemptible. <hi>When the vileſt men are exalted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 12.8.</note> 
               <hi>then the wicked walk on every ſide: then ſervants ride upon horſeback, and Princes walk as ſervants upon Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Mean perſons have commonly tyrannical, ſordid and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting ſpirits, and are of a baſe and mercenary diſpoſition. None ſo inſolent, ſo ſcornfull and unſufferable, as ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons generally, when they get into place or power. Not that Noble qualities are the inſeparable or ſole attendants of perſons otherwiſe Nobly born: if I ſhould ſay ſo, I ſhould hardly be able to maintain it. Nobility therefore here, is not reſtrain'd or appropriated to a bare external relation: it principally includes the <hi>better part of Nobility,</hi> ſo that the other is alwayes to be underſtood in conjunction with this. And may they ever go together, as things which God hath joyn'd, and never be put aſunder!</p>
            <p>But 'tis high time I came to ſome more <hi>ſpecial and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular application,</hi> and more immediately referring to the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, God himſelf hath made the application; 'tis he that hath put new life and vigour into the fainting ſpirits of a dying and deſpairing people.</p>
            <p>'Twas our happineſs, the bleſſedneſs of our Land, and can be no leſs then the joy and triumph of our ſouls, that <hi>as on this day</hi> to us a Son was born,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>May</hi> 29. 1630.</note> who is every way <hi>the Son of Nobles,</hi> Heir to a Prince Noble in all the ſenſes in which that word hath any commendable uſe. <hi>Noble</hi> by the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent luſtre of moſt Royal and renowned <hi>Anceſtors: Noble</hi> by thoſe eminent <hi>qualities</hi> that become ſo high a deſcent. Whatever either Art or Nature, Grace or Vertue, Reaſon or Religion might contribute to make a man truely noble, was eminently remarkable in that moſt Noble perſon and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated ſaint his <hi>Royal Father,</hi> to the great honour of him whoſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168912:18"/>Vicegerent he was, to the ſingular ſatisfaction of his friends &amp; Loyal ſubjects; to the ſhame and confuſion of his enemies, even to the wonder and admiration of all. <hi>Noble,</hi> for his zeal to Gods Houſe, and for his love to an unthankfull people. <hi>Noble</hi> in his <hi>life,</hi> and more <hi>noble</hi> in his <hi>death,</hi> made ſo by a Martyrdom ſo neer in reſemblance to that of the faithfull Witneſs in heaven, that 'twould be hard to finde any ſo exact a parallel in all the Annals and Records of time. But ſo it pleaſed God to make him, like his Saviour, <hi>perfect</hi> through ſufferings; by which he had the honour of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Victory in ſubduing the very malice it ſelf even of his bittereſt enemies. For ſuch was his patience and charity, ſuch his meekneſs and conſtancy, ſuch his prudence and fortitude, ſuch his ſanctity and piety, that even the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours themſelves were conquered, and being ſtript of all their hypocritical pretences, ſo as to have no cloak left for their ſin, expos'd ſtark naked with the greateſt ſhame to the contempt and ſcorn both of God and men: For no ſooner was he lifted up, but he drew all men unto him.</p>
            <p>Such was the Father, ſuch alſo is the Son, <hi>Nobilis ex Nobili,</hi> if not in the eyes and hearts of his own Subjects, yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly of ſtrangers and foraigners. For 'tis poſſible that a King as well as a Prophet, ſhould not be <hi>without honour ſave in his own Countrey.</hi> And had not his worth and excellency ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſomething more then ordinary, far above the uſual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments of great perſons, even thoſe of his own rank, it cannot be imagined how he ſhould ever have been able to keep up ſo long ſo great a reputation in ſuch a depreſs'd condition, and when ſo many <hi>blinde</hi> and <hi>ſecret</hi> arts have been uſed, ſo much <hi>open</hi> ſlander and detraction uttered to ſtain and eclipſe his glory, by thoſe <hi>filthy men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 8, 11, 13,</note> 
               <hi>who like raging waves of the Sea caſt up their own filth,</hi> and ſhall periſh in the <hi>gainſaying of Korah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Commonly as men are outwardly proſperous and ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo they are deem'd inwardly to be either wiſe or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous. The rich man thinks all that are poor are fools; and they that only admire wealth, neither know nor are capable of any other wiſdom. But true wiſdom is juſtified
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:168912:19"/>of her Children: and how much ſoever vertue in the general be of ſmall account, little conſidered and leſs exerciſed, yet there is a Charm ſometimes accompanying it, by which it hath ſo powerfull and ſecret an influence (as ſome perſons have the judgement or felicity to manage it) upon the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections even of the leaſt concern'd, that at forceth them into ſome degrees not only of love and honour, but of wonder alſo. The truth is, he that would be an accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht perſon throughout, muſt not content himſelf with thoſe external graces that render him acceptable to the firſt acquaintances and converſations of men, but be well ſtor'd with thoſe inward, ſolid endowments, which commend themſelves rather by the conſiderableneſs of their effects and after-conſequences, then by the cecency and elegance of their preſent appearances.</p>
            <p>And though 'tis poſſible for men to attain by their great care and practiſe ſome tolerable meaſures of both; yet the perfection of either is ſeldom attained without ſome neglect of the other.</p>
            <p>'Tis a wonder, I confeſs, how perſons of great and high birth, (conſidering their many and unavoidable diverſions; beſides the eminence of their condition, by which they are ſomewhat juſtly, but unhappily priviledg'd, from the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of a ſtrict, but advantageous diſcipline) ſhould make any farther benefit or progreſs, then what is imputable to the arbitrary and uncertain improvements of Chance: Yet, if Divine Providence have ſo contriv'd out of it's infinite pity and goodneſs to a Nation, that <hi>a Son of Nobles</hi> in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects ſhall be their <hi>bleſſing</hi> and their <hi>King:</hi> and that people ſhall be happy, not only by the force of his Precepts, but, the influence of his Example; if we are not the happieſt people upon the face of the earth, it is our own fault, that neither do nor will know in this our day the things that do belong unto our peace. For what can more be done for us then God hath already done? When we <hi>all like Sheep were gone aſtray, wandring up and down as thoſe that have no ſhepheard,</hi> made a prey to Lyons, and Bears, and Wolves, and Foxes, even all the beaſts of the people, God hath been
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168912:19"/>pleaſed, miraculouſly to put us under the conduct of one ſo fit, ſo ready and prepar'd to feed us, <hi>according to the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of his heart, and guide us by the skilfulneſs of his hands:</hi> who (beſides a moſt excellent knowledge both of men and things, which renders him a perfect Maſter of the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and the object of their praiſes, that have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to obſerve and revere ſo great a Majeſty in ſo ſweet a preſence graced with a happy and full concurrence of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ornaments) doth by a ſpecial bleſſing and more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate priviledge, lay ſo juſt a claim to that, which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath determined to be the perfection of Kings, in what he hath teſtified of <hi>David</hi> the Father, and <hi>Solomon</hi> the Son, who were the moſt eminent and glorious of all the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kings but he, who after he had in ſcorn been called by his malicious and implacable adverſaries <hi>the pretended King,</hi> one that ſaid he was the King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> did yet far exceed and tranſcend them all, as was then acknowledg'd even by thoſe contradicting and blaſpheming ſinners, when God had made his foes his footſtool.</p>
            <p>Now 'twas, you know, King <hi>Davids</hi> honour to be ſtyled frequently <hi>a man after Gods own heart,</hi> by his love to God, to his houſe and ſervice, by his eminent Juſtice, Clemency and Integrity. Yet the matter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> was very ſcandalous and reproachful to him. By the grace of God, and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his Holy Spirit, our <hi>David</hi> ſtands yet, and we have no cauſe to doubt, but by the power of the ſame grace he will continue to ſtand, to the laſt, untainted with any ſuch guilt. Then as for his fidelity and integrity both to God and man, he hath all along given ſuch ſignal evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, as even ſlander it ſelf is no longer able to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>For a perſon ſo variouſly afflicted, ſo diveſted of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward incouragements, ſo ſurrounded with the ſtrength of the moſt violent temptations, ſo conſtantly aſſaulted with all the force and ſubtilty of the moſt importunate attempts, to be ſo immoveable and conſtant in his Religion, as that neither the ſeaſonable <hi>kindneſs</hi> of thoſe of a <hi>contrary</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, nor the ſcandalous <hi>unkindneſs</hi> of thoſe of the <hi>ſame</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:168912:20"/>faith (either of which in a far leſſe degree is an engine ſtrong enough to batter the reſolution of a boaſting Phariſee) ſhould ever yet be able to ſtartle him; as it is no doubt an argument of greateſt joy and rejoycing to himſelf, ſo muſt it be of higheſt conviction and ſatisfaction to others. It is more over notoriouſly evident, that the great value and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which he hath for thoſe that have given conſtant and undoubted aſſurance of <hi>their Loyalty</hi> otherwiſe, could never yet inſinuate <hi>their vices</hi> into his favour and connivance; but he hath and doth ſo manifeſtly declare himſelf an enemy to thoſe ſcandalous ſins of ſome of them, to wit, <hi>ſwearing and debauchery,</hi> that all pretenders to the honour of good Subjects, muſt henceforth in good earneſt either reſolve to be ſober, or quit the reputation and reward of ſtrict and ſevere Loyalty.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Solomon</hi> the Son and Succeſſor of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 3.6.</note> you know what was his Petition to Almighty God, upon his taking poſſeſſion of the Throne of the Kingdom, as alſo the ſucceſs he had in that his requeſt, which was ſo pleaſing to God, and proved ſo beneficial and honourable to himſelf. And no queſtion but wiſdom and underſtanding are moſt eſſential qualifications of an accompliſh'd Prince, without which he cannot well <hi>goe either in or out himſelf,</hi> and muſt therefore be content <hi>to be led by others</hi> before ſo great a people. So gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in this particular hath God been unto us, in ſetting this Sacred perſon to Rule over us, that we may well ſay what was ſaid of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in another caſe, <hi>The Lord hath not dealt ſo with any Nation,</hi> among the heads whereof it would not be eaſie to finde ſuch a ſolidity of judgement, as needs not (out of any neceſſity) be forc'd either to depend on others, or diſtruſt it ſelf, but freely determine and ſtand to its own ſentence, and that firmly and ſteddily, without any fickleneſs or aptneſs to be toſs'd and turned about like a Ship without helm or balaſt, with every puff of Fancy or Conjecture. Moreover, what the Holy Scripture hath ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely declared, <hi>That he who walketh uprightly walketh ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> his Majeſties example hath moſt exactly verifyed, by giving a moſt undenyable inſtance that there is ſomething
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:168912:20"/>more in Wiſdom then Cunning, and that truth of Religion maketh the <hi>wiſeſt,</hi> becauſe the <hi>beſt</hi> men.</p>
            <p>But then all theſe excellencies not being the effect only of meer ſtudy and ſedentary ſpeculation, muſt needs become ſo much the more expedite, ready and uſefull, by how much the more they have been confirmed and increaſed by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent encounters and negotiations with perſons of ſo many different Nations and profeſſions, and of ſo contrary intereſts, by an unwearyed vigilance and induſtry, in a full employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and exerciſe of the ſtrength and powers both of his minde and body. And all this in complyance with a life of duty, in a neer ſubſervience to the great Majeſty of Heaven, and governed alſo by the exacteſt rules of an impartial juſtice, with that preſence, ſtrength and vigour of ſpirit, which dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers do not terrifie, nor any ſufferings or indignities diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, nor the croſs determinations of the all-ruling Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence caſt into the weak impatience of a mean deſpondency or abjection of minde.</p>
            <p>And then when we conſider what you all have ſeen, &amp; your own eyes or ears can witneſs from <hi>his own Declaration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>April</hi> 4/14 1660</note> how mercifull he is to his enemies, how pitifull and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as well to the follies and provocations, as to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and ſufferings of his ſeduced people, it muſt needs be ſaid of us as of ſome perſons, like our ſelves, ignorant of their own felicities, <hi>O fortunati nimium!</hi> we ſhould be even too happy, could we but underſtand it. The truth whereof will, I doubt not, through Gods bleſſing ere long become ſo evident, that albeit there be ſcarce faith to be found in the earth, it will yet be eminently and moſt fully verified even to the ſhame and conviction of the moſt incredulous.</p>
            <p>For my own part, I ſhall only add at preſent, that <hi>I have not ſpoken all this by hear-ſay,</hi> and can therefore the more eaſily believe, that it will ſoon be found to be no flattery: ſhould a perſon coming from far, as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> did, ſay alſo to him, as ſhe did there to <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 King. 10.8. <hi>Happy are thy men, happy are theſe thy ſervants that ſtand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually before thee, and that hear thy wiſdom! Bleſſed be the Lord thy God, which delighted in thee, to ſet thee on the Throne
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:168912:21"/>of Iſrael! Becauſe the Lord loved Iſrael for ever, therefore made he thee King to do judgement and juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which thou that art the King of Kings, by whom</hi> Kings reign, and Princes decree Juſtice, <hi>grant that he may conſtantly perform; and that we his Subjects, du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering whoſe Authority he hath, may faithfully ſerve, honour, and humbly obey him, in thee and for thee, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy bleſſed Word and Ordinance, who with thee and the Holy Ghoſt liveth and reigneth ever one God world without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
